你知道他们在争论什么吗?
Do you have any idea what they were arguing about?
你会说英语吗?
Do you speak English?
会
Yeah.
不过抱歉,我的德语不太好
No. I'm sorry,my German is not very good.
你听说过年龄会导致夫妻间失去互相倾听的能力吗?
Have you heard that as couples age they lose their ability to hear each other?
没有
No.
理论上男人会丧失听高音的能力...
Supposedly, men lose their ability to hear high-pitched sounds...
...而女人会丧失低音听力
...and women lose hearing in the low end.
这是一种相互抵制
I guess they nullify each other.
我想是的,自然法则是让夫妻白头偕老...
I guess. Nature's way of allowing couples to grow old together...
...而不是互相残杀
...without killing each other.
你在看什么书?
What are you reading?
哦
Oh, yeah.
你呢?
How about you?
我打算去休息室
I was thinking about going to the lounge car.
-你愿意和我一起去吗?   -好啊
-Would you like to come with me? -Yeah.
好的
Okay.
你的英语怎么说得这么好?
How do you speak such good English?
我在洛杉矶上过一个暑期班
I went to school for a summer in Los Angeles.
-坐这好吗?   -好的
-It's fine here? -Yeah, this is good.
我还在伦敦呆过一段时间
And I spent some time in London.
-哇  -那你的英语怎么说得这样好呢?
-Wow. -How do you speak such good English?
我?我是美国人
Me? I'm American.
-你是美国人?你肯定?  -当然
-You're American? Are you sure? -Yeah.
开个玩笑,我早知道你是美国人
No, I'm joking.I knew you were American.
而且你不会说任何其他语言,是吗?
And you don't speak any other language, right?
是的,是的,我知道你的意思
Yeah, yeah.I get it, I get it.
我是拙劣,弱智,粗俗的美国人...
I'm the crude, dumb,vulgar American...
...不会说其他语言,没有自己的文化,但我尝试过
...who doesn't speak other languages,who has no culture. But I tried.
我在高中学过法语,我第一次去巴黎...
I took French in high school.When I first got to Paris...
...在地铁站排队时
...I stood in line at the metro station.
一直练习--(法语)
I was practicing.
不管是什么
Whatever.
轮到我时,我看着那个售票员...
And I get up there,and I look at this woman...
...脑子一片空白,然后我说"我要一张票去..."
...and my mind goes blank. And I say,"I need a ticket to get to...."
话说回来...
So anyway....
你是去哪?
So where are you headed?
回巴黎
Well, back to Paris.
-我下周就要开学了  -你还在上学?什么学校?
-My classes start next week. -You're still in school? Where?
巴黎大学,听说过吗?
La Sorbonne. You know?
当然
Sure.
你从布达佩斯来?
You're coming from Budapest?
-我去看过我的祖母  -她人好吗?
-I was visiting my grandmother. -Oh. How is she?
事实上我对此颇感自豪
Well, I mean, I eventually kind of took pride in it.
就好象生命是我自己创造的
You know, like my life was my own doing.
就象我是盛宴上的不速之客
You know, like I was crashing the big party.
可以这样看待
That's the way to see it.
我父母仍在一起,我猜他们很幸福
My parents are still married and I guess they're happy.
不过我觉得未雨绸缪是正确的做法
But I think it's healthy to rebel against everything that came before.
知道吗,最近我很好奇...
You know, I've been wondering lately...
...你认识什么婚姻幸福的人吗?
...do you know anyone who's in a happy relationship?
当然,我认识一些幸福的夫妇
Yeah, sure. You know,I know happy couples.
可我认为他们在互相欺骗
But I think they lie to each other.
是啊
Yeah.
人们能在谎言中生活一辈子
People can live their whole life as a lie.
我的祖母结了婚...
My grandmother was married...
...我以为她有份简单的爱情生活
...and I thought she had an uncomplicated love life.
但她向我承认,她穷其一生...
But she just confessed to me that she spent her whole life...
...在梦想着她爱的另一个男人
...dreaming about another man she was in love with.
她屈从于命运,这太可悲了
She just accepted her fate.It's so sad.
但我也很高兴她有那种情感...
In the same time, I love that she had these emotions...
...而我从没想过她会有
...and feelings I never thought she had.
我敢说那样更好
I guarantee you it was better that way.
一旦了解了他,她最终会对他感到失望
If she'd known him, he'd have disappointed her eventually.
-你怎么知道?   -我当然知道
-How do you know? -I know. I know.
人们将浪漫想象得高于一切
People put romantic projections on everything.
那没有任何事实依据
It's not based in any kind of reality.
浪漫想象?哦,摩天轮里的就是浪漫先生啦?
Romantic projections?Oh, Mr. Romantic up in the Ferris wheel?
"哦,吻我吧,日落是多么美丽啊"
"Oh, kiss me. The sunset.Oh, it's so beautiful."
说说你祖母吧,你刚才是怎么说的?
Tell me about your grandmother.What were you saying about her?
看他们的口型
Check these guys out.
"汉斯,我要做忏悔,我没穿内衣"
"Hans, I have a confession. I'm not wearing underwear underneath this."
"哦,是吗?这让你害怕了?"
"Oh, really? Does that frighten you? "
可以告诉你个秘密吗?
Can I tell you a secret?
当然
Yeah.
过来
Come here.
-什么?  -过来
-What? -Come here.
这个看手相的看起来挺有趣
Look at this palm reader.She's interesting looking.
是的
Yeah.
-噢 -怎么了?
-Uh-oh. Uh-oh. -What?
-她注意到了  -她不会过来的
-I made eye contact.  -She's not coming over here.
-不,她会 -哦,见鬼
-Yes, she is. -Oh, shit.
哦,不
Oh, no.
-你想看手相吗?-不
-You want your palm read? -No.
挺好的
She's okay.
-身体还好吧?  -还不错
-She's all right? -She's fine.
-你呢?你去哪?  -我去维也纳
-How about you? Where are you going? -I'm going to vienna.
维也纳?那里怎么样?
vienna?What's there?
不知道,我明天就会离开
No idea.I'm flying out of there tomorrow.
你在渡假?
You're on holiday?
要知道我也不清楚这算不算渡假
I don't really know what I'm on.You know?
我只是四处旅行,坐了两三个星期的火车
I've just been traveling around,riding trains for two or three weeks.
是去拜访朋友还是纯粹的旅行?
You were visiting friends or just on your own?
我有个朋友在马德里,不过...
I had a friend in Madrid, but....
-马德里,那儿很漂亮  -我有张全欧火车优惠票...
-Madrid, that's nice. -I got a Eurail pass...
...就是这样
...is what I did.
不错的理由
hat's great.
那这次环欧旅行对你有帮助吗?
So has this trip around Europe been good for you?
是的,当然,它...它很有快感
Yeah, sure. It's been....It sucked.
什么?
What?
它有它的...
It's had its....
这么说吧,坐上几个礼拜来看窗外的景色...
I'll tell you, sitting for weeks on end looking out the window...
...感觉的确很不错
...has actually been kind of great.
你是指什么?
What do you mean?
你知道的,比如说...
Well, you know, for instance...
...会想到一些平时想不到的想法
...you have ideas that you ordinarily wouldn't have.
-什么想法?   -想听一个吗?
-What kind of ideas? -Want to hear one?
-说说看   -好的
-Tell me. -All right.
我有这个想法是因为一个电视节目
I have this idea, okay,for a television show.
我有个朋友是"享受电视"栏目的制作人
Some friends of mine are cable-access producers.
知道它的运作方式吗?
Do you know what that is?
他们播放任何人制作的低成本节目
Anybody can produce a show real cheap,and they have to put it on.
我的想法是让一个节目24小时播放并持续一年
I have this idea for a show that lasts 24 hours a day for a year straight.
你要做的就是找到...
What you do is you get...
...来自世界各地不同城市的365个人...
...365 people from cities all over the world...
...为每个人拍一部24小时的生活纪录片
...to do these 24-hour documents of real time.
捕捉真实的生活画面
Capturing life as it's lived.
知道吗,可以从一个人早上起床开始...
You know, it would start with a guy waking up in the morning...
...舒舒服服洗个澡...
...and taking the long shower...
...吃点早餐,喝点咖啡...
...eating a little breakfast,making a little coffee...
...看看报纸...
...reading the paper....
等一下,全都是大家见鬼的生活中每天那些平淡无聊的琐事吗?
Wait. All those mundane,boring things everybody has to do every day of their fucking life?
是"诗意的日复一日的生活"
I was going to say,"The poetry of day-to-day life."
你有你的说法,我有我的说法
You say it your way.I'll say it my way.
-你肯定?  -我肯定
-Are you sure? -I'm sure.
-好吧  -你好
-Okay. -Hello.
她来了
Oh, here she is.
我想要你看个手相
I want your palm read.
行,多少钱?
Yeah. How much is it?
算你50
For you, 50.
行吗?
Okay?
行
Okay.
你正在旅行...
So you have been on a journey...
...你不是本地人
...and you're a stranger to this place.
你是个...
You are...
...冒险家
...an adventurer.
一个探索者
A seeker.
你内心中有个冒险家
An adventurer in your mind.
你对女性的力量很感兴趣
You are interested in the power of the woman.
还有女性潜在的力量和创造力
In the woman's deep strength and creativity.
你正在成为这种女人
You're becoming this woman.
你需要摆脱自己拙劣的生活
You need to resign yourself to the awkwardness of life.
只有找到内心深处的宁静...
Only if you find peace within yourself...
...才能找到和别人的真正关联
...will you find true connection with others.
你和他并不熟是吗?
That is a stranger to you?
我想是的
I guess so.
你不会有事,他正在学习
You will be all right.He's learning.
好了
Okay.
给钱
Money.
你们都是星宿
You're both stars.
别忘了
Don't forget.
当星星在亿万年前爆炸时...
When the stars exploded billions of years ago...
...它们形成了世上的一切
...they formed everything that is this world.
我们认识的一切都是星尘
Everything we know is stardust.
所以别忘了,你们也是
So don't forget, you are stardust.
这很不错
That's very nice and all.
我是指我们都是星尘
I mean, that we're all stardust...
...而你会成为一个伟大的女性
...and you're becoming this great woman.
不过我希望你不要太当真...
But I hope you don't take that any more seriously...
...和报纸上的占卜相比
...than some horoscope in a newspaper.
为什么?她知道我在渡假,还知道我们互不相识
What? She knew I was on vacation and that we didn't know each other...
...还有我会成为一个伟大的女人
...and that I was going to become this great woman.
那"我在学习"是什么鬼话?
But what was that "l am learning" bullshit?
那是些套话,明白吗?
That's way condescending, you know?
当时她并没看我的手
I mean, she wasn't even doing me.
如果投机取巧者真是那样必须说真话的话
I mean, if opportunists like that ever had to tell the real truth...
...他们就会失业
...it would put them out of business.
我乐意看到一个瘦小老妇把她的所有积蓄...
Just once, I'd love to see some little old lady save up all her money...
...拿去算命,到那后算命的女人说...
...to go to the fortuneteller. She'd get there and the woman would say...
-可以这样想--  -有谁会看呢?
-Think of it like this-- -Who's gonna watch?
可以这样想,一只狗在太阳底下睡觉...
Think about it like this. Why is it that a dog sleeping in the sun...
...画面很美是不是?是的,确实很美
...is so beautiful?It is. It's beautiful.
但一个人从提款机取钱...
But a guy taking money from a bank machine...
...为什么就显得无聊了呢?
...looks like a complete moron?
这就象国家地理杂志的节目,只不过拍的是人
So it's like a National GEographic program, but on people.
正是
Yeah.
觉得怎么样?
What do you think?
是的,我明白,就象,"无聊24小时"--对不起--
Yeah, I can see it.Like, 24 boring hours-- Sorry--
...在一段3分钟的性交场面之后主角就睡着了
...and a three-minute sex scene where he falls asleep right after.
对啊,那会是一段很不错的情节
Yeah, and that would be a great episode.
人们会谈论这段情节
People would talk about that episode.
如果愿意的话你可以和朋友在巴黎拍上一集
You and your friends could do one in Paris if you wanted.
我不知道,关键是地理分布问题让我头疼
I don't know. The key, the thing that haunts me is the distribution.
要一个城镇接一个城镇地拍摄以保证它的持续性
Getting these tapes from town to town so it would play continuously.
因为它必须不停地播放,否则就没有意义了
Because it would have to play all the time, or it just wouldn't work.
谢谢
Thank you.
Thanks.
知道吗?没有"服务指南"
You know what?Not service oriented.
只是一份"欧洲观察"
Just an observation about Europe.
我父母从没真正谈论过我会恋爱结婚生孩子的可能性
My parents never really spoke of the possibility of my falling in love or getting married or having children.
甚至我还是小女孩时...
Even as a little girl...
...他们就要我考虑未来的职业,例如...
...they wanted me to think as a future career as a, you know...
...室内设计,律师或诸如此类
...interior designer or lawyer or something like that.
我对我爸爸说我想以写作为业
I'd say to my dad, "I want to be a writer."
他就说做记者
And he'd say, "Journalist."
我说想开个流浪猫收容所,他就说做兽医
I'd say I wanted to have a refuge for stray cats. He'd say, "veterinarian."
我说想做演艺工作,他就说做电视播音员
I'd say I wanted to be an actress.He'd say, "TV newscaster."
这使得我的理想抱负慢慢转变成了...
It was this constant conversion of my fanciful ambition into these...
...现实的赚钱手段
...practical moneymaking ventures.
我很小时就善于洞察谎言
I had a good bullshit detector when I was a kid.
当别人说谎时我总是能知道
I always knew when they were lying to me.
到了高中,我决定...
By high school, I was dead set...
...听听大家认为我这辈子该做什么...
...on listening to what everybody thought I should do with my life...
...然后反其道而行之
...and doing the opposite.
没有谁会当真,我只是不喜欢别人将想法强加在我头上
Nobody was ever mean about it.I just could never get very excited about other people's ambitions for my life.
"明天和你的下半辈子...
..."Tomorrow and all your remaining days...
"...会和今天全然相同...
...will be exactly like today...
"...在无聊中度日
...a tedious collection of hours.
"你不会有新激情和新想法
And you will have no new passions and no new thoughts...
"...没有新历程
...and no new travels.
"一旦死去就会被完全遗忘
And when you die,you'll be completely forgotten.
"请给50先令"
Fifty schillings, please."
这是我乐意看到的
That I'd like to see.
这太有意思了...
It's so funny how...
...她竟然没怎么注意你,不知是为什么
...she almost didn't notice you.It's weird. I wonder why.
她睿智而且热情,我很喜欢听她说的话
She was really wise and intense.I really loved what she said.
你是花钱来听让自己感觉良好的话
You pay your money to hear what makes you feel good about yourself.
维也纳也许有什么穷街陋巷能买到毒品
Maybe there's a seedy section of vienna.We can buy a hit of crack.
那不是更好?
Would you like that?
你也太...
You're so....
星尘,星尘
Stardust. Stardust.
有个展览
There's an exhibition.
我们赶不上了,要下周才开始
I guess we'll miss it.It doesn't start until next week.
看来是这样
Yeah, I think so.
其实我在博物馆见过这个
I actually saw this one in a museum.
我一直盯着它看
I stared and stared at it.
足足有45分钟
Must have been 45 minutes.
我喜欢它
I love it.
La Voie Ferree,真漂亮
La voie ferree.It's great.
我喜欢这种人物溶入背景的方式
I love the way the people are dissolving into the background.
看这个
Look at this.
似乎环境...
It's like the environments...
...比人物还要强烈
...are stronger than the people.
他的人物轮廓总是很简略
His human figures are always so transitory.
有意思吧,简略?
It's funny. Transitory?
简略
Transitory.
-你觉得开门没有?  -不知道,试试看
-You think this is open? -I don't know. Let's try it.
我到过一家这样的教堂...
I was in an old church like this...
...几天前在布达佩斯和我祖母一起
...with my grandmother a few days ago in Budapest.
尽管我排斥大部分宗教的东西...
Even though I reject most of the religious thing...
...可还是不自觉地感受到来这的人...
...I can't help but feeling for those people that come here...
...迷失,痛苦,内疚...
...lost or in pain, guilt...
...在寻求某种答案
...looking for some kind of answers.
能同时容纳那么多代人的痛苦和快乐的地方令我着迷
It fascinates me how a single place can join pain and happiness of so many generations.
...
你和祖母很亲近?
You're close with your grandmother?
是的
Yeah.
大概是因为我经常有种奇特的感觉...
I think it's because I always have this strange feeling...
但你知道吗?如果父母从不...
But you know what?If your parents never...
...在任何事上完全否定你,而是友好地给予支持...
...fully contradict you about anything and are nice and supportive...
Right.
对
...那会让你很难抱怨
...it makes it even harder to officially complain.
哪怕他们做得并不对,这是一种被动攻击
Even when they're wrong,it's this passive-aggressive shit.
你明白吗?
You know what I mean?
我讨厌这样
I hate it.
非常反感
I really hate it.
知道吗,尽管这种种不快...
Well, you know, despite all that kind of bullshit...
...总是会随之而来
...that comes along with it...
...但我记得童年就象...
...I remember childhood as...
...一段魔幻时光
...this magical time.
真的,记得我妈妈第一次跟我说到死亡
I do. I remember when my mother first told me about death.
我的曾祖母去世,我们全家去弗罗里达奔丧
My great-grandmother had died, and my family had visited them in Florida.
当时我才3岁或3岁半
I was about 3, 3 1/2 years old.
我在后院玩耍时...
Anyway, I was in the back yard playing...
...姐姐教我怎样拿浇花的水管...
...and my sister had just taught me how to take the garden hose...
...就是象这样子捏着...
...and do it in such a way that...
...喷出的水雾会在阳光下形成一道彩虹
...it sprayed into the sun and would make a rainbow.
于是我那样做...
And so I was doing that...
...透过水雾,我看到了曾祖母
...and through the mist,I could see my grandmother.
她就站在那,冲着我微笑
And she was just standing there,smiling at me.
我愣在那很长时间
And I held it there for a long time...
...并且看着她
...and I looked at her.
最终我松开了喷嘴
And then finally, I let go of the nozzle, you know?
然后扔下水管...
And then I dropped the hose...
...她就消失了
...and she disappeared.
于是我跑回屋里告诉父母
And so I run back inside and tell my parents.
他们让我坐下,然后训斥了我一顿...
And they sit me down and give me this big rap on how...
...人死了之后你绝不可能再见到他们,那只是我的幻觉
...when people die, you never see them again, and how I'd imagined it.
但我知道我看到了什么,并且为之高兴
But I knew what I'd seen.I was glad I saw that.
我以后绝不会再看到类似的情景,但我不知道
I've never seen anything like that since. But I don't know.
那让我有点明白世事都是那么无法解释
It just kind of let me know how ambiguous everything was.
包括死亡
Even death.
你该庆幸你能这样看待死亡
You're lucky you can have this attitude toward death.
我想我时刻都在害怕死亡
I think I'm afraid of death 24 hours a day.
真的,所以我才会坐火车
I swear. I mean, that's why I'm in a train right now.
我可以乘飞机去巴黎,但我害怕
I could've flown to Paris,but I'm scared.
-不会吧   -我控制不了
-Oh, come on. -I can't help it.
...我是那个躺着垂死的衰老妇人
...that I'm this very old woman laying down, about to die.
知道吗,我的生活就是...
You know, that my life is just...
...她的记忆或是什么
...her memories or something.
这太疯狂了
That's so wild.
我时常觉得自己仍然是13岁的小孩...
I always think that I'm still this 13-year-old boy...
...不知道怎么做成年人,装模作样...
...who doesn't really know how to be an adult, pretending to...
...过自己的生活,逼不得已时做做笔记
...live my life, taking notes for when I'll really have to do it.
仿佛是穿着戏服在演一场初中话剧
Like I'm in a dress rehearsal for a junior high play.
真有趣
That's funny.
那么在摩天轮上时,就象是...
Then up there in the Ferris wheel,it was like...
...垂老妇人吻了一个小男孩,是吗?
...this very old woman kissing this very young boy. Right?
你知道贵格教徒和贵格教的宗旨吗?
Do you know anything about the Quakers, the Quaker religion?
不太清楚
No, not much.
我参加过贵格教徒的婚礼...
Well, I went to this Quaker wedding once...
...感觉很奇特
...and it was fantastic.
他们的做法是...
What they do is...
...新人走进去跪在所有来宾的面前...
...the couple comes in and they kneel in front of the whole congregation...
...然后彼此凝视
...and they stare at each other.
没人说话,除非他们觉得是上帝要他们交谈或发言
Nobody says a word unless they feel that God moves them to speak or say something.
然后,经过大约一小时...
And then, after an hour or so of just...
...相互凝视...
...staring at each other...
...就成了夫妻
...they're married.
太美了,我喜欢这样
That's beautiful. I like that.
有个可怕的故事
This is a horrible story.
是什么?
What?
这里不适合讲这事
It's not the appropriate place to tell it.
我曾和一个朋友开车兜风
Well, I was driving around with this buddy of mine.
他是个坚定的无神论者
He's a big atheist, you know.
他在一个流浪汉身旁停下车
And he came to a stop next to this homeless guy.
然后掏出100美元...
My buddy takes out a $ 100 bill...
...探出车窗...
...and leans out the window...
...问道,"你相信上帝吗?"
...and he says,"Do you believe in God? "
那个人看看我的朋友,看看钱
And the guy looks at my friend,he looks at the money.
说道...
He says...
..."是的,我相信"
..."Yes, I do."
我朋友说,"回答错误"
My friend says, "Wrong answer."
然后开车走了
We drove away.
太可恶了
That's mean.
如果你不下火车,现在该到巴黎了吧?
Would you be in Paris by now if you hadn't gotten off the train?
不,还没到
No, not yet.
那你会做些什么?
What would you be doing?
也许会在机场逗留...
I'd probably be hanging around the airport...
...因为你不在而对着咖啡哭泣
...crying in my coffee because you didn't come with me.
也许我会在萨尔茨堡和别人下车
I'd probably gotten off the train in Salzburg with someone else.
哦,是吗?我懂了
Oh, yeah? Oh, I see.
我只是个愚蠢的美国人...
So I'm just a dumb American...
...只能用来当作临时点缀,是吗?
...momentarily decorating your blank canvas, huh?
-我玩得很开心  -是吗?
-I'm having a great time. -Really?
我也是
Me too.
我很高兴没人知道我在这
I'm glad, because no one knows I'm here.
不认识能告诉我你做过的所有坏事的人
I don't know anyone that would tell me all those bad things you've done.
-我可以告诉你  -我相信
-I'll tell you some. -Yeah, I'm sure.
听过太多坏事之后我总觉得...
You hear so much shit about people.I always feel like...
...赴约时象个将军
...the general of an army when I start dating.
制订好战略战术
Plotting my strategy and maneuverings...
...了解他的弱点,什么能伤害他,征服他
...knowing his weak points,what would hurt him, seduce him.
真是恐怖
It's horrible.
如果我们一直呆在一块...
If we were always around each other...
...那我第一件能令你发疯的事是什么?
...what would be the first thing about me that would drive you mad?
不,我不想回答这个问题
No. I'm not going to answer this question.
有个和我约会过的姑娘经常问我...
I dated this girl once who used to always ask me that.
"我哪方面让你发疯?"
"What about me bugs you? "
最后我说,"我觉得你的批评方式不太好"
Finally I said, "l don't think you handle criticism too well."
她勃然大怒和我分了手,这是真的
She flew into a rage and broke up with me. That's true.
其实她是要找个借口...
All she wanted was to have an excuse...
...来告诉我她不该和我交往
...to tell me what she thought was wrong with me.
你也想这样吗?
Is that what you want?
我哪些方面让你发狂?
Something about me bugs you?
-我有什么会令你崩溃?  -根本没有
-What is it about me bugs you? -Nothing at all.
如果非要说的话,会是什么?
If it had to be something,what would it be?
如果非得有,而我非得考虑的话...
If it had to be something,if I had to think about it...
...我不太喜欢你对看手相的反应
...I kind of didn't really like this reaction at the palm reader.
就象只好斗的公鸡
You were like this rooster prick.
什么叫好斗的公鸡?
What the hell is a rooster prick?
你象个哭闹的孩子...
You were like a boy whining...
...因为所有注意力都不在你身上
...because all the attention wasn't focused on him.
好吧,听着,那女人蒙蔽了你,对吗?
All right, listen.This woman robs you blind, okay?
你象个路过冰淇淋店的小孩...
You were like a boy walking by an ice-cream store...
...因为妈妈不给他买奶昔而哭闹
...crying because his mom won't buy him a milk shake.
我不在乎那江湖骗子说过什么--
I don't care what this charlatan has to say about--
什么?
What?
我懂一点,但他不懂,抱歉
I understand a little,but he doesn't at all.
能问你个问题吗?
May I ask you a question?
我想和你们做个交易
So I would like to make a deal with you.
我不直接向你们要钱,而是让你们说一个词
I mean, instead of just asking you for money, I will ask you for a word.
你们给我一个词,然后我会写一首诗
You give me a word, I take the word,and then I will write a poem...
...将它包含在内
...with the word inside.
如果你们喜欢我的诗...
And if you like it,if you like my poem...
...觉得它能给你们的生活增添色彩...
...if it adds something to your life in any way...
...那就随意给我一些报酬
...then you can pay me whatever you feel like.
当然,我会用英语来写
I'll write in English, of course.
-行   -行,很不错
-Okay. -All right. Great.
那么?
So?
选个词吧
Pick a word.
一个词
A word.
-奶昔  -奶昔?哦,不错
-Milk shake. -Milk shake? Oh, good.
-我想说"好斗公鸡"的,不过挺好,奶昔   -奶昔?
-I was gonna say "rooster prick." But great. Milk shake.  -"Milk shake"?
好的,奶昔
Okay, milk shake.
好了,那么...
-All right, so.... -Good.
我喜欢这个维也纳人变相的乞讨方式
I gotta say, I like this viennese variation of bum.
我喜欢他"给生活增添色彩"那句话
I like what he said about adding something to your life.
我们刚才是不是有了第一次争执?
So, were we having our first fight back there?
我觉得是争执过
I think so. I think we were.
就算有,为什么大家都觉得冲突很糟糕呢?
Even if we were, why does everyone think conflict is so bad?
争执能带来很多好的事物
There's a lot of good things coming out of conflict.
对,我也这样想
Yeah, I guess so.
我常想如果自己能面对现实...
I always think if I could just accept the fact...
...面对生活中可以预见的艰难之处...
...that my life was supposed to be difficult, that's what's expected...
...也许就不会那么郁闷
...then I might not get so pissed off.
遇到好事时会为之高兴
And I'd just be glad when something nice happens.
所以我还在上学
That's why I'm still in school.
这样可以提高竞争能力
It's easier to have something to fight against.
我们骨子里都有这种强烈的好胜心
Well, we've all had such competitiveness ingrained in us.
你也知道,我可以做一些无聊的事
You know, I can be doing the most nothing thing.
投飞镖或是打台球
Throwing some darts or shooting some pool.
然后很自然地产生这种想法
Then all of a sudden,I feel it come over me.
我必须赢
I have got to win.
你邀我一起下车也是出于好胜心吗?
Is that why you tried to get me off the train? Competitiveness?
你是指什么?
What do you mean?
写好了
I got a poem.
哦,是吗
Oh, all right.
能念给我们听吗?
Will you read it to us?
当然可以
Sure. Okay.
白日梦般的错觉
"Daydream delusion
豪华车竟有睫毛
Limousine eyelash
哦,宝贝,你的脸如此美丽
Oh, baby, with your pretty face
坠一滴泪入我的酒杯看着那双大眼睛
Drop a tear in my wine glass Look at those big eyes
明白到你对我的意义
See what you mean to me
犹如蛋糕和奶昔
Sweetcakes and milk shakes
我是迷人的天使
I am a delusion angel
我是奇幻的展台
I' m a fantasy parade
想让你明白我的心思不要再继续猜量
I want you to know what I think Don't want you to guess anymore
你不知我来自何处
You have no idea where I came from
我们不知该前往何方
We have no idea where we're going
只管融入生活
Lodged in life
就象河流的支脉
Like branches in the river
奔腾而下,随波逐流
Flowing downstream Caught in the current
我中有你
I carry you
你中有我
You'll carry me
就该是这样
That's how it could be
你明白我了吗?
Don't you know me?
现在你明白我没有?
Don't you know me by now? "
太棒了
Great.
-谢谢   -谢谢,伙计
-Thanks. -Thanks, man.
给你
Here you go.
-谢谢   -不用
-Thanks. -All right.
-给,谢谢你   -谢谢
-Here. Thank you. -Thank you.
祝你好运
Good luck.
写得很棒,是吧?
It was wonderful, no?
-怎么了?   -那可能不是他写的
-What?   -He probably didn't just write that.
也许他只是加了一个词进去
He wrote it, but he probably plugs that word in.
不管是"奶昔"还是什么
You know, whatever, "milk shake."
你想说什么?
What do you mean?
没什么,我喜欢,很不错
Nothing. I loved it. It was great.
知道什么让我发疯吗?人们谈论...
You know what drives me crazy?People talking about...
...科技如何伟大,如何节省时间
...how great technology is,how it saves all this time.
但节省了时间却变得更加忙碌,不加以利用又有何意义呢?
But what good is saved time if nobody uses it?If it just turns into more busy work.
从没听人说要用文字处理器节省的时间去寺庙游玩
I never hear anybody say, "With the time I've saved using my word processor I'm gonna go to a Zen monastery and hang out
-从没听说过  -时间太抽象了
-You don't hear that. -Time is so abstract anyway.
-你在看那个女孩?  -什么?
-Are you looking at this girl? -What?
没什么
Nothing.
想进去吗?
You wanna go in here?
-想不想进去?  -行啊,是夜总会对吧?
-You wanna go in here? -Yeah. It's a club, no?
进去?
Wanna go?
你好
Hello.
50先令
Fifty schillings.
-每个人  -我这有100,给
-Each.  -I got 100. Here, I got it.
我请你喝啤酒,谢谢
I'll buy you a beer. Thank you.
-你请我喝啤酒?  -对
-You gonna buy me a beer? -Yeah.
这里的美国啤酒贵不贵?
You think Old Milwaukee is expensive here?
我们还没说过你是否正在和谁交往吧?
We haven't talked about this yet,but are you dating anyone?
例如有男朋友什么的正等着你回巴黎
You got a boyfriend waiting on you back in Paris or anything like that?
-不,现在没有  -但以前有
-No, not right now. -But you did.
我们6个月前分手了
We broke up six months ago.
6个月前?哦,真遗憾
Six months ago? Oh, I'm sorry.
这话题就不那么有趣了,说说看
I mean, I'm not that sorry.Tell me about it.
不,太无聊了我不想说
No way. I can't.It's really, really boring.
来吧,跟我说说
Come on. Tell me about it.
好吧,我很失望
I was really disappointed.
原以为能维持一段时间,可他...
I thought this one would last for a while. He was...
...愚蠢,粗鲁,没情趣,酗酒....
...very stupid, ugly,bad in bed, alcoholic....
纯粹是个草包
-You know.-A real prize winner.
我是想给他留点面子
I was kind of giving him a favor.
但他离开了我,说什么我太爱他...
But he left me,saying I loved him too much.
妨碍了他的所谓狗屁艺术表现力
I was blocking his artistic expression or some shit like that.
不管怎样,我很受伤害,变得--
But anyway, I was traumatized and became--
由于他而变得很困惑
And became totally obsessed with him.
所以去看心理医生,编了个...
So I went to a shrink, and it came up that I had written...
...关于女人想杀死她男友及如何下手的愚蠢故事...
...this stupid story about this woman trying to kill her boyfriend and how she'd do it.
...所有怎样下手又不会被抓的细节
It's all the details of how to do it and not get caught--
她想杀死男朋友?
She was gonna kill her boyfriend?
是的,我不会真去做,只是编的罢了
Yeah, she was. It's nothing I would do,but it was just some writing.
是的,我明白
No, I understand.
愚蠢的医生相信了我说的一切
This stupid shrink believed everything I told her.
是我第一次就诊,她说必须通知警察
It was my first time seeing her.She said she had to call the police.
她必须通知警察?
She had to call the police?
她完全相信我会付诸行动
She was totally convinced I was really gonna do it.
即使我解释那只是我编造的
Even though I had explained it was just some writing.
她看着我的眼睛说"你说的这些...
She said, looking into my eyes,"The way you said it...
...我知道你会去做"
...I know you are going to do it."
她纯粹是疯了
She was totally out of her mind.
那是我唯一一次看心理医生
It was my first and last session.
那么后来呢?
So what happened then?
我彻底忘记了他
I totally got over him.
现在我烦恼的是...
But now, I'm obsessed...
...如果他死于千里之外的一场事故
...that he's gonna die from an accident or 1000 kilometers away.
受指控的将是我
And I'm gonna be the one accused.
为什么我们会为不那么喜欢的人感到困惑呢?
Why is it you become obsessed with people you don't really like that much?
不知道
I don't know.
那你呢?
So how about you?
-什么?  -和谁在一起?
-What?  -Are you with anyone?
我们一直回避这个话题可真滑稽
It's funny how we managed to avoid this subject for so long.
可你现在得告诉我
But now you have to tell me.
我对爱的注脚是--
Well, I kind of see love...
两个不知该如何独处的人的庇荫
...as this escape for two people who don't know how to be alone.
真有趣,人们总是说...
It's funny.People always talk about how...
...爱是完全无私的付出
...Iove is this totally unselfish,giving thing.
但细想想却除了自私什么都没有
But if you think about it,there's nothing more selfish.
我明白
I know.
那么,你刚和谁分手?
So who just broke up with you?
什么?
What?
听起来你象是受了伤害
You sound like you just were hurt.
我?
Do I?
好吧
All right.
我承认
Big confession.
我应该早告诉你的
I should've told you this earlier or something.
我来欧洲不只是为了..
I didn't come to Europe just to...
...在巴黎散心,读海明威
...hang out and read Hemingway in Paris and shit like that.
整个春季我都在攒钱,想去马德里...
I saved up my money all spring to fly to Madrid...
...和我的女友共渡夏季...
...and spend the summer with my girlfriend--
-你的女友?   -前女友
-Your girlfriend? -My ex-girlfriend...
...过去一年来她一直在学艺术史
...who has been on this art history program for the last year.
总之,我到了这,久别重逢...
Anyway, I got here.We were reunited at long last...
...第一晚是和她的6个朋友一起出去吃饭
...and we went out to dinner our first night with six of her friends.
佩德罗,安东尼奥,冈萨罗...
Pedro, Antonio, Gonzalo...
...玛丽娅,老乡苏茜
...Maria, Suzy from home.
好几天她都设法回避和我独处...
She managed to avoid being alone with me for the first few days...
...慢慢我意识到她并不希望我来
...and I stuck around just to let it sink in that she wished I hadn't come.
于是买了从维也纳起飞的最便宜的机票
So I bought the cheapest flight out,this one leaving out of vienna.
几周内没有航班,所以我又买了火车票
It didn't leave for a couple weeks,so I bought this Eurail pass.
知道别人和你分手最糟糕的事是什么吗?
You know what's the worst thing about somebody breaking up with you?
是当你记起自己很少想到...
It's when you remember how little you thought about...
...与之分手的人,并意识到...
...the people you broke up with,and you realize...
...他们也很少想到你
...that that is how little they're thinking about you.
你以为双方都会感觉痛苦...
You'd like to think you're both in pain...
...实际上却是"嘿,很高兴你离开"
...but really, they're just,"Hey, I'm glad you're gone."
相信我,我懂
Believe me, I know.
你该注意积极的一面
You should look at bright colors.
是那个心理医生告诉我的
That's what the shrink told me.
我付她900法郎1小时...
I was paying her 900 francs an hour...
...来倾听我是个杀人狂
...to hear that l was a homicidal maniac...
...如果我注意积极的一面就能消除我的困惑
...but I could shift my obsession if I would concentrate on bright colors.
管用吗?
Did it work?
-对玩弹球没帮助  -对,没有
-Didn't help your pinball. -Well, no.
是的,要知道最近我没杀任何人
Yeah, well, you know,I haven't killed anyone lately.
近来没有?
Not lately?
真不错,你康复了
That's good.You're cured then.
有种猴子,它们整天都在交配...
There's breeds of monkeys,and all they do is have sex...
...从早到晚
...all the time.
它们因此而最少攻击性...
And they turn out to be the least violent...
...最平和,最快乐
...the most peaceful, the most happy.
所以鬼混未必就是坏事
So maybe fooling around's not so bad.
-你是在说猴子吧?  -是啊
-Are you talking about monkeys? -Yes, I am.
-我想也是  -怎么?
-I thought so. -Why?
我从没听说过,这恐怕是雄性为他们鬼混找的完美借口
I never heard this one.But it reminds me of this perfect male argument to justify them fooling around.
母猴子也可以啊,大家都可以
Women monkeys are fooling around too.Everybody's fooling around.
真有趣,我有个可怕而偏激的念头...
That's cute. I have this awful,paranoid thought...
...女权主义是男人创造的,好让他们...
...that feminism was mostly invented by men so they could...
...更方便鬼混
...fool around more.
"女人,解放头脑,解放身体,和我睡觉
"Woman, free your mind,free your body. Sleep with me.
"我们都是快乐自由的,只要能满足我的色欲"
We're all happy and free, as long as I can fuck as much as I can."
好了,好了
All right.
这也许包含有生物学的因素
But maybe there's some biological things at work here.
如果你有个岛...
If you had an island...
...岛上有99个女人和1个男人...
...and there were 99 women on the island and only one man...
...1年后也许会多出99个孩子
...in a year, you'd have the possibility of 99 babies.
但如果岛上是99个男人和1个女人...
But if you have an island with 99 men and only one woman...
...1年后就只可能有一个孩子,所以....
...in a year, you have the possibility of only one baby. So....
你知道吗?
You know what?
我猜岛上也许只会留下43个男人
On this island, I think there will be only, like, maybe 43 men left.
为了和那可怜的女人性交他们会互相残杀
They would've killed each other trying to fuck this poor woman.
而另一个岛上会有99个女人,99个孩子
And on the other island,there would be 99 women, 99 babies...
...但不再有男人
...and no more man.
因为她们会把他生吃掉
Because they would've all eaten him alive.
哦,是吗?
Oh, yeah?
对此可以这样说
There's something to that.
某种程度上,女人并不介意毁掉一个男人
On some level, women don't mind the idea of destroying a man.
我曾和我的前女友一起逛街...
I was walking down the street with my ex-girlfriend...
...有4个长相凶恶的人站在一辆跑车附近
...and we'd just walked by these four thuggy-looking guys next to a Camaro.
其中一个说"嘿,宝贝,屁股真漂亮"
And one of them says,"Hey, baby. Nice ass!"
我觉得"这没什么,没必要为此生气"
So I'm like, "No big deal.I won't get uptight about this."
对,而且他们有4个人
Plus, there were four of them.
就是,可她说"去你妈的,混蛋"
Exactly. But she says,"Fuck you, dickheads!"
我想,"这下好了,等着瞧吧"
And I'm like, "Okay.Wait a minute, here."
他们可不会过来踢她的屁股
They're not gonna come over and kick her ass.
那么谁会被顶到前线上去呢?
So who just got pushed to the frontline on that one?
女人说她们讨厌被严加保护
Women say they hate it if you're all protective.
如果照她的意思去做,又说你不是男人
But if it suits them, then they'll tell you you're being unmanly.
知道吗?我不认为女人真的想毁掉男人
You know what? I don't think woman really wants to destroy man.
即使她们想也不会成功
Even if they want to,they don't succeed.
我相信恰恰是男人在毁掉女人...
I'm sure even men are destroying women...
...或者说相对而言更有能力毁掉女人
...or are capable of destroying women much more than women--
总之,这令人沮丧,懂我意思吗?
Anyway, it's depressing.You know what?
-你想停止这个话题?  -我讨厌这些
-You wanna stop talking about this? -I hate it.
男人,女人,这...
Men, women, it's....
永无休止,就象...
There's no end to it.
就象张跳针的唱片
It's like a skipping record.
凡是夫妻都会永远讨论这问题
Every couple's been having this conversation forever.
但没人能得出结论
And nobody came up with anything.
我看过记录片说这是生育舞蹈
I saw a documentary on that.It's a birth dance.
生育舞蹈?
A birth dance?
我该给她钱吗?
Should I give her some money?
所有有意思的事都要花钱
Everything that's interesting costs a little money.
生育舞蹈,是吧?
So a birth dance, huh?
在我看来有点象交配舞蹈
Looked a little bit like a mating dance to me.
不,是真的,女人临盆时就跳这个
No, but really.Women used it when giving birth.
世上仍有一部分人这么做
In part of the world,they still do it.
临产的女人进到帐蓬里...
The woman in labor enters a tent...
...同部落的女人围着她跳舞
...and the women of her tribe surround her and dance.
并鼓励她一起跳
They encourage her to dance with them...
...可以减轻分娩的痛苦
...so as to make the birth less painful.
孩子降生后大家一起起舞庆贺
And when the baby is born,they all dance in celebration.
我猜我妈妈可不会这样做
I don't think my mom would've gone for that.
我喜欢跳舞这类所有人都能参与的活动
I like the idea of dancing as something everybody participates in.
我知道,我听说有个老头...
I know. I heard about this old guy...
...他看到年轻人在跳舞
...who was watching some young people dance.
说道,"真美
He said, "How beautiful.
"他们甩掉生殖器以变成天使"
They're shaking off their genitals to become angels."
有意思
I like that.
不过有个问题
One question, though.
当女人们全身心地投入到舞蹈中时...
When the women are dancing and being all spiritual and stuff...
...男人们在哪?
...where are the men?
出去找食物了?没被邀请?还是女人不需要男人?
Are we out food gathering? Are we not invited? You all don't need us?
男人该庆幸没在交配后被咬下头颅
Men are lucky we don't bite off their heads after mating.
实际上象蜘蛛什么的会那样做
Certain insects do that,like spiders and stuff?
能活着还有什么可抱怨的呢?
We let you live.What are you complaining about?
你这是危言耸听,话里有话
See, you're officially kidding.But there's something to that.
你一直在强调某些观点
You keep bringing stuff like that up.
不,没有,等一等,说正经的
No, no. Wait a minute.Talking seriously here.
我一直觉得要做一个坚强而独立的女强人...
I mean, I always feel this pressure of being a strong and independent icon of womanhood...
...不让自己的全部生活围着某个男人转有很大的压力
...and not making it look like my whole life is revolving around some guy.
但是爱一个人和被人爱对我来说意味着很多
But loving someone and being loved means so much to me.
我常拿这类事情说笑...
I always make fun of it and stuff...
...可并非我们做的每件事...
...but isn't everything we do in life...
...都能赢得更多的爱
...a way to be loved a little more?
我不知道
I don't know.
有时候我梦想着...
Sometimes I dream...
...做一个好父亲好丈夫
...about being a good father  and a good husband.
而且有时候会觉得很接近了
And sometimes it feels really close.
可另外一些时候...
But then other times...
...这想法似乎很蠢
...it seems silly...
...仿佛它会
...like it would...
...毁掉我全部的生活
...ruin my whole life.
不是由于对责任感的畏惧...
And it's not just a fear of commitment...
...或是没有能力去关爱,因为
...or that I'm incapable of caring or loving because...
...我能胜任
...I can.
如果我绝对公正地对待自己...
It's just that, if I'm totally honest with myself...
...那我宁死也不想知道...
...I think I'd rather die knowing...
...我擅长些什么
...that I was really good at something.
比起仅仅维系一份良好的,友爱的关系来说,还有哪些方面更突出
That I had excelled in some way than that I'd just been in a nice, caring relationship.
我曾为一个老人工作,有次他告诉我...
I had worked for this older man,and once he told me...
...他把一生的心思都放在了事业上
...that he had spent all of his life thinking about his career.
52岁时他突然地发现...
He was 52,and it suddenly struck him...
...他从没为自己做过任何事
...that he had never really given anything of himself.
他这辈子毫无作为
His life was for no one and nothing.
他说这话时都要哭了
He was almost crying saying that.
我相信如果有神存在...
I believe if there's any kind of God...
...不会存在于任何人身上
...it wouldn't be in any of us...
...不会是你或者我
...not you or me...
...而是存在于这小小的空间之中
...but just this little space in between.
如果世上有什么奇迹...
If there's any kind of magic in this world...
...一定是尽力理解某个人,并与之同甘共苦
...it must be in the attempt of understanding someone sharing something.
我知道,这几乎是不可能成功的
I know, it's almost impossible to succeed...
...可谁真正在乎呢?
...but who cares really?
答案一定是在尝试之中
The answer must be in the attempt.
我想文明正在衰亡,看看这服务吧
I think this is a civilization in decline. Look at the service.
侍者在哪?在纽约她肯定得失业
Where is the waitress?In New York, she'd be out of a job.
我来给巴黎的一个朋友打电话
I'm gonna call my friend in Paris...
...我想约她午休时一起吃饭
...who I'm supposed to have lunch with in eight hours.
接电话
Pick up.
-接电话啊  -好的
-Pick up the phone. -All right.
我正学英语,你说英语行吗?当作消遣
I've been working on my English.You wanna talk in English, for laughs?
行,这主意不错
Yeah, okay. That's a good idea.
我今天不能陪你吃午饭了,对不起
I don't think I'll be able to make it for lunch today.
我在火车上认识了一个人,和他在维也纳下了车
I met a guy on the train,and I got off with him in vienna.
你疯了吗?
Are you crazy?
也许吧
Probably.
-他是不是奥地利人?  -不,不是
-He's Austrian? He's from there? -No, No.
是个游客,美国人,明天一早就要回家
He's passing through. He's American.He's going back home tomorrow.
你为什么下车?
Why'd you get off?
他说服了我
Well, he convinced me.
实际上我在火车上和他聊过一阵之后...
I mean, actually, I was ready to get off the train with him...
...就打算和他一起下车
...after talking to him a short while.
他很有趣,让我情不自禁
He was so sweet, I couldn't help it.
在休息车厢,他谈到...
In the lounge car,he began to talk about...
...他小时候见过他曾祖母的鬼魂
...him as a boy seeing his great-grandmother's ghost.
我就是那时被他吸引住了
I think that's when I fell for him.
就因为一个小男孩和他所有的美丽梦想
Just the idea of this little boy with all those beautiful dreams.
他征服了我
He trapped me.
而且他很可爱
And he's so cute.
他有漂亮的蓝眼睛...
He has beautiful blue eyes...
...漂亮的粉红色嘴唇...
...nice pink lips...
...油腻的头发
...greasy hair.
我很喜欢
I love it.
他高高的个子,有点笨拙
He's kind of tall,and he's a little clumsy.
我喜欢他偷偷看我的感觉
I like to feel his eyes on me when I look away.
他接吻时象个青涩少年,很可爱
He kind of kisses like an adolescent.It's so cute.
-不是吧?  -就是,我们接过吻,感觉非常棒
-What?  -Yeah, we kissed. It was so adorable.
随着夜色降临,我越来越喜欢他
As the night went on,I began to like him more and more.
我担心他有点怕我
I'm afraid he's scared of me.
我跟他说过一个女人想杀死前男友的故事
I told him the story about the woman that kills her ex-boyfriend.
他肯定怕得要命
He must be scared to death.
他一定以为我是个专横歹毒的女人
He must be thinking I'm this manipulative, mean woman.
但愿他不会这样认为
I just hope he doesn't feel that way about me.
因为,你了解我,我决不会伤害别人
Because, you know me,I'm the most harmless person.
唯一能真正伤害的只有我自己
The only person I could really hurt is myself.
我不认为他会怕你
I don't think he's scared of you.
我想他对你很着迷
I think he's crazy about you.
-真的?  -我认识你很久了
-Really? -I've known you a long time.
对你印象很好,你还会再见他吗?
I got a good feeling.You gonna see him again?
我们还没提到这个问题
We haven't talked about that yet.
好,到你了,打电话给你的朋友
Okay, it's your turn.You call your friend.
好的,好的
All right, all right.
通常只能接通他的答录机
I usually get this guy's answering machine.
嘿,哥儿们,什么事?
Hi, dude. What's up?
弗兰克,过得怎样?真高兴你在家
Hey, Frank. How you been?I'm glad you're home.
挺好,是的
Cool. Yeah.
马德里怎么样?
So how was Madrid?
没劲透了
Madrid sucked.
莉莎和我总算彻底玩完了
Lisa and I had our long overdue meltdown.
太糟了,我早说过不是吗?
Too bad. I told you, no?
对,相隔太远从不会有结果
Yeah, yeah. The long-distance thing just never works.
我只在马德里呆了几天
I was only in Madrid for a couple days.
我买了张最便宜的机票
I got a cheaper flight out of vienna.
实际上并不太便宜,只不过...
You know, it really wasn't that much cheaper. I just....
我不能马上回家,我不想见到任何熟人
I couldn't go home right away.I didn't want to see anybody I knew.
只想变成完全不为人知的游魂
I just wanted to be a ghost,completely anonymous.
你现在还好吧?
So are you okay now?
对,我很好,很好,真的
Yeah. I'm great. I'm great.That's the thing.
我很开心
I'm rapturous.
告诉你是为什么
And I'll tell you why.
在欧洲最后一晚我认识了一个人
I met somebody on my last night in Europe.
-难以置信  -我知道,我知道
-That's incredible. -I know, I know.
有句老话说我们是对方的魔鬼和天使
You know how they say we're all each other's demons and angels?
她无疑是波提且利画笔下的天使
Well, she was literally a Botticelli angel...
...告诉我一切都会好起来
...telling me everything would be okay.
你们怎么认识的?
How did you meet?
是在火车上
On the train.
她邻座的一对古怪夫妻在吵架
She was sitting next to a weird couple that was fighting...
...她换座时正好坐在过道对面
...so she moved. She sat right across the aisle from me.
于是我们开始聊天
So we started to talk.
起初她不太喜欢我
She didn't like me much at first.
她非常聪明...
She's super smart...
...充满激情...
...very passionate...
...而且很漂亮
...and beautiful.
我却太缺乏自信
And I was so unsure of myself.
我觉得我说的话都很蠢
I thought everything I said sounded so stupid.
哦,伙计,这我并不担心
Oh, man. I wouldn't worry about that.
她不会因此而对你有成见
No, I'm sure she was not judging you.
再说了,她坐到了你旁边
No, and by the way,she sat next to you.
我相信她是有意如此
I'm sure she did it on purpose.
哦,是吗?
Oh, yeah?
我们男人太蠢了,一点也不了解女人
Us men are so stupid. We don't understand anything about women.
她们行为古怪,我只知道这一点
They act strange,the little I know of them.
对不对?
Don't they?
我觉得我们象是处在梦境之中
I feel like this is some dream world we're in.
对,这很奇怪
Yeah, it's so weird.
仿佛我们在一起的时间只属于我们
It's like our time together is just ours.
是我们自己创造的
It's our own creation.
就象我在你梦里,你在我梦里
It must be like I'm in your dream and you're in mine.
所以这一整夜才会如此美妙...
And what's so cool is that this whole evening...
...客观地说我们本来是不会在一起的
...all our time together,shouldn't officially be happening.
我明白,所以才会感觉象在童话世界
Yeah, I know. Maybe that's why this feels so otherworldly.
不过天亮之后我们就会变回南瓜,对不对?
But then the morning comes and we turn into pumpkins, right?
我明白
I know.
但是现在,你该拿出玻璃鞋...
But now, you're supposed to produce the glass slipper...
...看看合不合适
...and see if it fits.
会合适的
It'll fit.
我有个朋友的孩子是在家里出生的,所以他在那帮忙
This friend of mine had a kkid and it was a home birth,so he was there helping out.
他说生命降生之时的意义非凡
But he said at that profound moment of birth...
...他看着他的孩子第一次体验生命
...he was watching his child experiencing life for the first time...
...试着第一次呼吸
...trying to take its first breath.
他能想到的却只是眼前这个生命总有一天将会死去
All he could think about was that he was looking at something that was gonna die someday.
他无法驱散这个念头
He couldn't get it out of his head.
我觉得很真实,一切事物都是有限的
And I think that's so true.Everything is so finite.
你是否觉得正因为这样...
But don't you think that's what...
...才使我们的时间和特殊时刻如此重要?
...makes our time and specific moments so important?
是的,我明白
Yeah, I know.
就象我们今晚一样
It's the same for us tonight, though.
过了明天,我们也许永远都不会再见面
After tomorrow, we'll probably never see each other again, right?
你不认为我们还能见面?
You don't think we'll ever see each other?
你觉得呢?
What do you think?
老实说,我不知道,我没有其他旅游计划
Actually, I don't know.I hadn't planned another--
我也是,我在巴黎,你在美国,我能理解
Me too. I live in Paris,you live in the U.S. I understand.
我不想让你来,你讨厌飞行不是吗?
I'd hate to make you fly.You'd hate to fly, right?
我并不那么害怕飞行
I'm not so scared of flying.
我是说我可以
I mean, I could.
是吗,如果你想...
Well, if you were gonna...
...来美国...
...come to the U.S...
...或者,也许我...
...or if, you know, if l....
我是说,我可以再来这
I mean, I could come back here.
怎么了?
What?
我们该以成年人的理性来对待这事
No, let's just be rational adults about this.
我们该尝试不同的方式
We should try something different.
就算今晚是我们仅有的一晚也不错不是吗?
It's not so bad if tonight is our only night, right?
大家交换电话,住址
People exchange numbers, addresses.
结果只通过一两封信,一两次电话
They end up writing once,calling each other twice.
是的,结果很糟
Right. Fizzles out.
我不想那样,我讨厌那样
Yeah, I don't want that.I hate that.
我也讨厌那样
I hate that too.
为什么大家都认为关系应该永远保持呢?
Why does everybody think relationships should last forever?
是啊,为什么?真蠢
Yeah, why? It's stupid.
你觉得今晚就是...
But you think tonight's it?
我是指,这就是我们仅有的一晚吗?
I mean, that tonight's our only night?
只能这样不是吗?
It's the only way, no?
那好吧
Well, all right.
就这样
Let's do it.
不欺骗,不猜忌
No delusions, no projections.
只管把今晚过好
We'll just make tonight great.
好,就这么办
Let's do that.
我们应该握握手
We should do some kind of handshake.
把手给我
Give me your hand.
为了我们唯一一个...
To our one and only...
...共处的夜晚...
...night together...
...以及余下的时间
...and the hours that remain.
怎么了?
What?
这真是...
It's just....
令人沮丧是不是?
It's depressing, no?
此刻我们唯一要想的就是...
Now, the only thing we're gonna think of is...
...我们必须说再见的时刻
...when we'll have to say goodbye.
可以现在就说,那样就不用担心了
We could say goodbye now.Then we won't worry about it.
现在?
Now?
说再见
Say goodbye.
-再见   -再见
-Bye.  -Goodbye.
再见
Au revoir.
-再见   -再见
-Later. -Later, yeah.
这样好了
Here's the plan.
你去偷杯子,我去弄酒
You're gonna grab the glasses,and I'm gonna get the wine.
-红酒  -红酒,行
-Red wine. -Red wine. Right.
-你觉得能弄到吗?   -别担心
-You think you can do that? -No problem.
-祝我好运   -祝你好运
-Wish me luck. -Good luck.
你好
Hello.
你会说英语吗?
Do you speak English?
-会一点  -会一点是吗?
-A bit.  -Yeah? A bit?
我有件棘手的事...
I'm having kind of an odd situation...
...是这样....
...which is that....
看到那边那女孩了吗?
You see that girl over there?
这是我们在一起的唯一一晚
Well, this is our only night together...
...而她...
...and she....
问题在于她想要瓶红酒...
The problem is that she wants a bottle of red wine...
...可是我身无分文
...and I don't have any money.
我想你也许能...
But I was thinking that you might want to...
...给我这家酒吧的地址,我保证...
...give me the address of this bar,and I would promise...
...寄钱给你,而你能成全我们这一夜
...to send you the money, and you'd be making our night complete.
-你会寄钱给我?  -是的
-You would send me the money? -Yes
你保证?
Your hand?
敬你一生中最美好的夜晚
For the greatest night in your life.
太感谢你了
Thank you very much.
我经常和别人一起分享美好时刻...
So often I've been with people and shared beautiful moments...
...例如旅游或彻夜不眠等着看日出
...like traveling or staying up all night and watching the sunrise.
我知道那都是特别的时刻
And I knew those were special moments.
但总有不如意的地方
But something was always wrong.
我希望是和另外的人在一起
I wished I'd been with someone else.
我知道那种感觉...
I knew that what I was feeling...
...实际上对我很重要,他们不会明白
...exactly what was so important to me,they didn't understand.
但我很高兴和你在一起
But I'm happy to be with you.
你不会知道为什么这样一夜...
You couldn't know why a night like this...
...对我的生活来说有多重要
...is so important to my life right now...
...但确实重要
...but it is.
这是个美妙的早晨
This is a great morning.
是个美妙的早晨
It is a great morning.
你觉得我们可以更进一步吗?
Do you think we have others like this?
那我们的理性和成年人的决定怎么办?
What about our rational, adult decision?
哦，是呀
Oh, yeah.
我明白你说的希望的人不在是指什么
I know what you mean about wishing somebody wasn't there.
通常,我自己...
It's just, usually, it's myself...
...会希望可以远远躲开
...that I wish I could get away from.
说真的,想想看
Seriously, think about this.
我从没去过任何...
I have never been anywhere...
...我没去过的地方
...that I haven't been.
从没有一个吻...
I've never had a kiss...
...是我没有吻过的
...when I wasn't one of the kissers.
从没有...
You know, I've never...
...看过我不在场时看过的电影
...gone to the movies when I wasn't there in the audience.
从没打过我没参与的保龄球
I've never been out bowling if I wasn't there...
...制造一些愚蠢的笑话
...making some stupid joke.
所以才会有那么多人讨厌自己,真的
That's why so many people hate themselves. Seriously.
他们渴望死亡...
It's just, they are sick to death...
...徘徊在自己周围
...of being around themselves.
如果我们一直呆在一起
Let's say that you and I were together all the time.
你会开始讨厌我的坏习惯
You'd start to hate a lot of my mannerisms.
包括...
The way...
...每次我们有客人来访...
...the way every time that we would have people over...
...我变得不可靠,我喝过了头
...I'd be insecure, and I'd get a little too drunk.
或是我反复讲些愚蠢,自作聪明的故事...
Or the way I tell the same stupid,pseudo-intellectual story...
...翻来覆去地说...
...again and again.
那些故事我都听过...
You see, I've heard all those stories...
...所以我当然会厌恶自己
...so of course I'm sick of myself.
但和你在一起...
But being with you...
...让我觉得自己象是另一个人
...it's made me feel like I was somebody else.
象这样能让人忘我的其他方法只有...
I mean, the only other way to lose yourself like that is...
...你也知道,跳舞...
...you know, dancing...
...酒精...
...or alcohol...
...毒品,诸如此类
...or drugs, or stuff like that.
做爱?
Fucking.
作爱,对,也是方法之一
Fucking, yeah. That's one way.
知道我想要什么吗?
Do you know what I want?
什么?
What?
有人吻我
To be kissed.
这我能做到
Well, I could do that.
等等
Wait.
我得说几句傻话
I have to say something stupid.
没问题
All right.
非常傻
It's very stupid.
我觉得我们不该发生关系
I don't think we should sleep together.
我很想,但以后我们永远都不会再见面
I want to, but since we're never going to see each other again...
...这让我很难受
...it'll make me feel bad.
我会猜你和谁在一起,会想你
I'll wonder who else you're with.I'll miss you.
我知道,这不太成熟
I know. It's not very adult.
也许是女人的天性,我控制不住
Maybe it's a female thing.I can't help it.
那我们就再见面
Let's see each other again.
我不希望你为了和我作爱而破坏约定
No, I don't want you to break our vow just so you can get laid.
我不只是想,而是--我是说...
I don't want to just get laid.I want to-- I mean....
我觉得我们应该作爱
I mean, I think we should.
我们早上就会死去不是吗?
We die in the morning, right?
-所以应该   -那就象男人的梦想
-I think we should. -Then it's like some male fantasy.
邂逅一个法国女郎,干了她然后永不再见
Meet a French girl,fuck her and never see her again.
而且有个好故事可说了,我可不想...
And have this great story to tell.I don't want...
...这个美好的夜晚变成那样
...this great evening to just have been for that.
好的,我们不用作爱,那没什么大不了
Okay, we don't have to have sex.It's not a big deal.
你不想再见到我?
You don't want to see me again?
不,我当然想
No, of course I do.
如果现在有人让我选择...
If somebody gave me the choice right now...
...永远不再见你还是娶你
...of to never see you again or to marry you...
...我会娶你
...I would marry you.
也许是所谓的浪漫过头
Maybe that's a lot of romantic bullshit...
但有人结婚的理由比这更少
...but people have gotten married for a lot less.
事实上...
Actually...
...我们下火车时我决定要和你睡觉
...I think I decided I wanted to sleep with you when we got off the train.
聊了这么多之后我拿不定主意了
Now that we've talked so much,I don't know anymore.
我们干嘛把一切变得这么复杂?
Why do we make everything so complicated?
我不知道
I don't know.
回到巴黎你首先想要做什么?
What's the first thing you'll do when you get back to Paris?
给父母打电话
Call my parents.
你呢?
What about you?
不知道,也许会去拿狗,它在我朋友那
I don't know. I'll probably go pick up my dog. He's with a friend.
你有只狗?我喜欢狗
You have a dog?I love dogs.
-是吗?  -是的
-You do? -Yeah.
-哦,该死  -怎么了?
-Oh, shit. -What?
说不清,我们回到现实中来了
I don't know.We're back in real time.
是的,令我讨厌
I know. I hate that.
是什么?
What is that?
听起来象古钢琴
Sounds like a harpsichord.
去看看
Check that out.
有人在演奏
Somebody's playing.
真酷
That's cool.
我们能随着琴声起舞吗?
Can we dance to the harpsichord?
当然
Of course.
哦，哇
Oh, wow.
怎么?
What?
我要拍下你的照片
I'm gonna take your picture...
...那就永远不会忘记你...
...so I never forget you...
...和这一切
...or all this.
好的,我也一样
Okay, me too.
"岁月会象兔子一样溜走"
"The years shall run like rabbits."
什么?
What?
没什么
Nothing.
我有张唱片是戴伦-托马斯...
I have this recording of Dylan Thomas
...朗诵W.H.奥登的诗
...reading a W. H. Auden poem.
他有副好嗓子
He's got a great voice.
比如...
It's like....
"城里所有时钟
"All the clocks in the city
"开始当当响着报时
Began to whirr and chime:
"不要让时间欺骗你
'O let not Time deceive you
"你不可能征服时间
You cannot conquer Time.
"在烦恼与忧虑之中
In headaches and in worry
"朦胧的生活消逝无踪
vaguely life leaks away
"时间占有了他的幻想
And Time will have his fancy
"明天或是今天"
Tomorrow or today.' "
就象这样
Something like that.
不错
That's good.
你说过在最初的几年之后...
When you talked earlier about after a few years...
...一对夫妻怎样开始彼此厌恶...
...how a couple would begin to hate each other...
...由于彼此太了解...
...by anticipating their reactions...
...或是厌倦了对方的恶习
...or getting tired of their mannerisms.
我觉得我恰恰相反
I think it would be the opposite for me.
我彻底了解一个人时就会真正爱上他
I think I can really fall in love when I know everything about someone.
他怎样梳理头发...
The way he's gonna part his hair...
...哪一天穿哪件衬衣...
...which shirt he's gonna wear that day...
...知道在什么场合他会说什么故事
...knowing the exact story he'd tell in a given situation.
这时候我肯定就爱上他了
I'm sure that's when I know I'm really in love.
-嘿,糟糕   -怎么了?
-Hey, guess what. -What?
我们没去看那场话剧
We didn't go to those guys' play.
话剧?
Play?
那头母牛?
The cow?
是啊,我们没去
Oh, yeah, we didn't.
哦,不,我们错过了
Oh, no. We missed it.
你知道去机场的公车吗?
You know what bus to take to the airport?
是的,别担心
No problem.
-我就上这趟车   -到了,你就上去吗?
-I should get on this one. -Right here. You wanna get on there?
那就这样了,是吗?
I guess this is it, no?
我真的...
I really....
-要知道...   -我知道,我也是
-You know.... -Yeah, I know. Me too.
祝你生活顺利,事事开心
Have a great life. Have fun with everything you're gonna do.
也祝你学业和一切顺利
Good luck with school and all that.
我知道统计显示"不,不,不,它很安全"
I know the statistics say,"Na, na, na, it's safer." Whatever.
但我乘飞机时就会看到爆炸
When I'm in a plane,I can see the explosion.
我看到我从云端坠落
I can see me falling through the clouds.
我非常害怕那几秒钟的意识...
And I'm so scared of those few seconds of consciousness...
...在临死之前,你知道自己快要死了的时候
...before you die.When you know you're gonna die.
我总忍不住会这样想
I can't stop thinking that way.
那让人筋疲力竭
It's exhausting.
是的,没错
Yeah, I bet.
真的筋疲力竭
Really exhausting.
-我想这是维也纳了   -是的
-I think this is vienna. -Yeah.
-你在这下,是吗?   -是的,真扫兴
-You get off here, no?  -Yeah, what a drag.
早认识你就好了,我很喜欢和你聊天
I wish I'd met you earlier.I really like talking to you.
我也是
Yeah, me too.
很高兴能认识你
It was really nice of you too.
我有个无疑是疯狂的想法,但要是不问你的话...
I have an admittedly insane idea,but if I don't ask you this...
...我下半辈子都会耿耿于怀的
...it'll haunt me the rest of my life.
是什么?
What?
我想继续跟你聊天,尽管我对你一无所知...
I want to keep talking to you.I have no idea what your situation is...
...但我觉得我们似乎...
...but I feel like we have some kind of...
似曾相识,同意吗?
...connection. Right?
是的,我同意
Yeah. Me too.
那就好,是这样
Right. Great.Here's the deal.
跟我一起下车游览维也纳
Get off here in vienna and come check out the town.
-什么?   -来吧,肯定很有意思
-What?  -Come on. It'll be fun.
-来吧   -我们做些什么?
-Come on. -What would we do?
不知道,我只知道我的飞机是明早9:30
I don't know. All I know is I catch a flight tomorrow morning at 9:30...
...而且我没钱住旅馆了,所以只好到处走走...
...and I can't afford a hotel,so I was going to walk around...
...如果你和我同行会更有意思
...and it'd be more fun if you came with me.
如果你觉得我不正常,你可以改乘下一班火车
And if I turn out to be a psycho,just get on the next train.
好吧,好吧,设想一下
All right, all right.Think of it like this.
10年20年之后,懂吗?
Jump ahead 10, 20 years, okay?
你结婚之后
And you're married.
你的婚姻失去了曾经有过的活力
Only your marriage doesn't have that same energy it used to have.
你开始责备你的丈夫
You start to blame your husband.
你回想你一生中曾遇见过的所有男人...
You think about all those guys you've met in your life...
...设想嫁给他们中的一个会发生什么
...and what might've happened if you'd picked up with one of them.
我就是其中之一,就是我
I'm one of those guys.That's me.
就当这是个时空旅行...
So think of this as time travel...
...来到现在,看看你当时错过了什么
...from then to now to find out what you're missing out on.
那会有极大的帮助,你会发现并未错过任何东西
What this could be is a gigantic favor to you and your husband to find out you're not missing anything.
我只是个和他一样的失败者,缺乏目标,无所事事
I'm just as big a loser as he is.Unmotivated. Boring.
你做了正确的选择,为此而开心
You made the right choice.You're happy.
我去拿我的包
Let me get my bag.
我们该找个地方寄存行李
We should get a locker for all this.
你叫什么?
What's your name?
我吗?
My name?
杰西,实际上是詹姆斯,但大家都叫我杰西
Jesse. James, actually,but everybody calls me Jesse.
那就是杰西-詹姆斯,对吗?
You mean, Jesse James, no?
不,就是杰西
No. No, just Jesse.
我叫塞琳娜
I'm Celine.
这座桥真漂亮
This is a nice bridge.
是的
Yeah.
感觉怪怪的
This is kind of weird.
是吗?我觉得有点尴尬
Isn't it? I mean,I feel a little awkward.
-但没关系不是吗?   -是的,这非常棒
-But it's all right. Right? -Yeah, this is great.
-找些地方看看吧  -好的,我们找找看
-Let's go to some places.  -Yeah, let's go to some places.
-我去问问这些人  -好的
-Let's ask these guys.  -Okay.
抱歉,打扰一下
Excuse me. Excuse me?
你们会说英语吗?
SprEchEn siE English?
-当然会  -能不能换成你说德语?
-Ja. Of course. -Do you speak German for a change?
-什么?  -开个玩笑
-What?  -No, it was a joke.
我们今天刚到维也纳,想找些有意思的地方看看
We just got into vienna today, and we' re looking for something fun to do.
例如博物馆,展览会...
Like museums, exhibitions....
但最近博物馆没什么意思
But museums are not that funny anymore these days.
他们马上就要关门了,你们会在这逗留多久?
They are closing right now.How long are you going to be here?
就一个晚上
Just for tonight.
你们为什么来维也纳?你们想看些什么?
Why did you come to vienna?What could you be expecting?
我们在渡蜜月
We' re on honeymoon.
是的,她怀孕了,我们不得不结婚...
Yeah, she got pregnant,we had to get married....
得了吧,你不懂撒谎
I don't believe you.You're a bad liar.
我们有场演出,很乐意邀请你们观看
This is a play we're both in.We would like to invite you.
你们是演员?
You're actors?
不是专业的,只是业余爱好
Not professional.Part-time for fun.
是关于一头母牛和寻找它的印第安人
It's a play about a cow and Indians searching for it.
另外还有政客,墨西哥人--
There are also politicians, Mexicans--
俄罗斯人,共产主义者...
Russians, communists....
-用真正的母牛表演吗?  -不,是由一个演员扮演
-You have a real cow on stage? -No, an actor in a cow costume.
-他演母牛  -是的,我演母牛
-He's the cow. -Yes, I am the cow.
-但这头牛有点古怪  -它得了一种病
-And the cow's a bit weird. -The cow has a disease.
它的行为有点怪异,象只狗
She's acting a bit strange.Like a dog.
有人扔根棍子的话,它会去叼回来
If someone throws a stick,she fetches it.
还能用蹄子抽烟什么的
And she can smoke with hoofs and everything.
-真有意思  -看,这个就是地址
-Great.  -As you see, there is the address.
在第二区
It's in the second district.
普拉特附近,知道是什么吗?
Near the Prater. You know it?
那个大摩天轮吗?我们会去的
The big Ferris wheel?We should go. We should.
你们可以在开演之前先去普拉特
Perhaps you can go to the Prater before the play.
演出是21:30开始
It starts at 2130.
-21:30?   -就是9:30
-2130?   -It's at 9:30.
-9:30  -好的
-9:30. -Oh, right.
这场戏叫什么?
What's the name of this play?
翻译过来就是"带给我威尔明顿的母牛角"
It translates as "Bring Me the Horns of Wilmington's Cow."
我就是威尔明顿的牛
I'm Wilmington's cow.
-好的  -太棒了
-All right. -Great.
-你们会来吗?  -尽量吧
-You'll be there? -We'll try.
我是母牛
I'm the cow.
再见
Goodbye.
我有个主意,你准备好没有?
I got an idea. Are you ready?
是个问答游戏,我们已经互相有所了解
It's Q and A time.We've known each other a little while.
我们是同伴了,所以可以相互问几个直接的问题
We're stuck together, so we'll ask each other a few direct questions.
行吗?
All right?
-我们互相提问?  -但你必须老实回答
-We ask each other questions? -And you have to answer honestly.
-当然   -好的
-Of course. -Okay.
好的,第一个问题
All right, first question.
-你问  -是的,我要求你...
-You.  -Yes, I am going to ask you.
描述一下第一次性经验是什么感觉
Describe for me your first sexual feelings towards a person.
我第一次的感觉?我的天
My first sexual feelings?Oh, my God.
我知道,我知道
I know. I know.
让-马克-弗勒里
Jean-Marc Fleury.
让-马克-弗勒里?
Jean-Marc Fleury?
我们一起参加夏令营,他是个游泳运动员
We were at this summer camp together,and he was a swimmer.
有一头被氯漂白的头发和绿眼睛
He had bleached-out chlorine hair and green eyes...
为了提高成绩他刮掉了腿上和手臂上的毛
...and to improve his times,he'd shave his legs and arms.
-真恶心   -就象只光洁的海豚
-That's disgusting.  -He was like this gorgeous dolphin.
我的朋友艾玛对他很着迷
My friend Emma had a big crush on him.
有一天,我穿过营地回我的房间
So one day, I was cutting across the field back to my room...
他走到我身边,我告诉他
...and he came walking up beside me.I told him...
"你该和艾玛约会,她对你很着迷"
..."You should date Emma.She has a big crush on you."
但他转过身对我说
And he turned to me and said...
"那太糟了,因为我对你很着迷"
..."Well, that's too bad, because I have a big crush on you."
是的,那真让我感到意外
So, yeah, it really scared the hell out of me...
...因为我觉得他太优秀
...because I thought he was so fine.
然后他正式向我提出约会,我假装不喜欢他
Then he officially asked me on a date.I pretended I didn't like him.
要知道我很害怕自己可能做的事
You know, I was so afraid of what I might do, you know.
我去看了几次他的游泳比赛
So I went to see him swim a few times at the competition.
他很性感,真的,我是说非常性感
And he was so sexy. Really.I mean, really sexy.
那个夏季末我们写下了一些爱的宣言
We wrote these little declarations of love at the end of the summer...
我们保证要一直通信
...and, you know, promised we would keep writing forever...
还有要尽快再见面
...and meet again very soon and--
见了吗?
Did you?
当然没有
Of course not.
我可以告诉你我是个非常棒的游泳选手
Then this is the opportune time to tell you I'm a fantastic swimmer.
-真的吗?   -当然
-Really?   -Yeah.
-我会记录下来   -没问题
-I make note of that.  -Okay.
-现在轮到我了吧?  -是的,轮到你了
-So it's my turn. No?  -Yes, your turn.
问吧
Hit me.
你曾经恋爱过吗?
Have you ever been in love?
是的
Yes.
下一个问题
Next question.
-是什么--  -等等
-What was the-- -Wait a minute.
-一个字就算是回答?  -怎么不算?
-So I can give one-word answers?  -Why not?
我可是详细描述过我初次的性经验
After I went into detail about my sexual feelings?
因为问题不同,我可以回答性体验的事
They' re different questions. I could answer the sexual-feelings thing.
但你要知道,爱-- 如果我问你是否恋爱过你会怎么回答?
But, you know, love-- I mean,what if I asked you about love?
我会说假话,但我至少会编造一个美妙的故事
I would have lied, but at least I would have made up a great story.
爱是个复杂的问题,明白吗?
Love is a complex issue, you know?
我想是的,我告诉过一些人我爱他们,而且我是认真的
I mean, yes, I've told somebody that I love them, and I've meant it.
但爱是完全无私的付出吗?
But was it totally unselfish,giving love?
爱是一件美好的事吗?
Was it a beautiful thing?
不完全是,它就象,爱...
Not really.
我想我无法说清
I mean, I don't know.
你明白吗?
You know?
-是的,我明白你的意思   -至于性体验...
-Yeah. I know what you mean. -But as far as sexual feelings go...
...是开始于一种迷恋性的关系...
...it started with an obsessive relationship...
...是和78年的7月小姐.你知道"花花公子"杂志吗?
...with Miss July, 1978.Do you know Playboy magazine?
-听说过   -知道克里斯托吗?
-I've heard of it. -You know Crystal?
你不知道克里斯托?哈,我认识她
You don't know Crystal?Well, I knew Crystal.
该轮到我了?
Is it my turn now?
告诉我一件你特别生气的事
Tell me something that really pisses you off.
-让你气得发疯   -让我生气
-Really drives you crazy.  -Pisses me off.
-老天,什么都让我生气  -列举一二
-God, everything pisses me off. -List a couple.
哦,我知道,我讨厌被陌生男人搭讪...
Oh, I know. I hate being told by strange men...
...街上的陌生男人...
...strange men in the street...
...你知道的,笑脸让他们觉得生活不那么无聊
...you know, to smile to make them feel better about their boring life.
还有呢?
What else?
我讨厌
I hate....
我憎恨远在千里之外的战争
I hate that 300 kilometers from here,there's a war...
...人们在死亡,但没人知道该怎么做
...people are dying,and nobody knows what to do.
也许根本不在乎,我说不清
Or they don't give a shit.I don't know.
我讨厌媒体试图控制我们的思想
I hate that the media's trying to control our minds.
-媒体?   -是的,媒体
-The media?  -Yeah, the media.
很难形容,是一种新的法西斯主义
It's very subtle, but it's a new form of fascism, really.
我讨厌...
I hate....
我讨厌身处异国,尤其是美国
I hate when I'm in a foreign country,especially in America...
...每当我穿黑衣服或是发脾气,说不着边际的话...
...each time I wear black or lose my temper or say anything about anything...
...他们总是说,哦,法国味十足,真有趣...
...they always go,"Oh, it's so French. It's so cute."
我讨厌这些,无法忍受,真的
I hate that.I can't stand that. Really.
就这些?
Is that all?
还有很多,不过...
Well, there's a lot of things, but....
-轮到我问了  -好的
-So it's my turn. -Okay.
-你得回答   -是的,我会回答
-You're gonna answer. -Yes, I'll answer.
什么会让你困惑呢?
What's a problem for you?
也许就是你
You, probably.
什么?
What?
有天我有过一个想法...
I had a thought the other day that kind of...
...那确实让我困惑
...qualifies as a problem.
是什么?
What is it?
是我在火车上想到的
It was a thought I had on the train, so....
这么说吧
Okay. All right.
你相信轮回转世吗?
Do you believe in reincarnation?
是的,那很有意思
Yeah. Yeah, it's interesting.
很多人都谈论前世这一类的话题
A lot of people talk about past lives and things like that, you know?
哪怕在特定的场合他们并不相信这一点...
And even if they don't believe in it in some specific way...
...人们相信灵魂是永存的
...people have a notion of an eternal soul.
-是的   -那好
-Yeah.  -Okay.
我的想法是,5万年前
This is my thought:50,000 years ago...
...人口还不足100万
...there's not even a million people.
1万年前有大约200万人口
Ten thousand years ago,there's, like, two million people.
而现在世界上有50到60亿人口
Now there's between five and six billion people on the planet.
如果我们都有属于自己独有的...
If we all have our own individual, unique...
...灵魂...
...soul...
...那他们是从何而来的呢?
...where did they all come from?
现代人的灵魂只是原有灵魂的一部分吗?
Are modern souls only a fraction of the original souls?
如果是的话,就表示每个灵魂在过去5万年...
If they are, that represents a 5000 to 1 split of each soul...
...分裂成了5000个,对地球而言只是一瞬间
...in the last 50,000 years, which is a blip in the Earth's time.
我们最多只是人类史上微不足道的一部分
So at best, we're these tiny fractions of people walking
所以我们才这么分散?所以我们才这么独特?
Is that why we're so scattered?Is that why we're so specialized?
等等,我不太--
Wait a minute, I'm not sure--
是的,我知道,这完全是不着边际的想法
Yeah, I know, I know.It's a totally scattered thought.
不过这样才有点意义
Which is kind of why it makes sense.
我同意
I agree with you.
我们还是下车吧
Let's get off this damn train.
这里很不错
This place is pretty neat.
是的
Yeah.
还有个试听室呢
There's even a listening booth.
听说过这个歌手吗?
Have you heard of this singer?
是美国人,有个朋友跟我提起过
I think she's American.A friend told me about her.
想看看试听室是否还能用吗?
Do you want to go see if that listening booth still works?
当然想
Yeah, okay.
~北面吹来一阵风
There's a wind that Blows in from the north
~诉说着爱意的来临
And it says that loving Takes this course
~来吧
Come here
~不,我并非不可亲近
No, I'm not impossible to touch
~我从未如此需要过你
I have never wanted you so much
~来吧
Come here
~是否我从未躺在你身旁
Have I never laid down by your side
~宝贝,让我们抛开矜持
Baby, let's forget about this pride
~来吧
Come here
看看这,太美了
Look at this. This is beautiful.
快,车要开了
Quick. It's leaving.
看,有只兔子
Look, there's a rabbit.
对
Yeah.
你好,兔子
Hey there, rabbit.
它真可爱
It's so cute.
我十多岁时来过这
I visited this as a young teenager.
它当时留给我的印象比博物馆更深
It left a bigger impression on me at that time than the museums.
是吗?它很小
Yeah? It's tiny.
我知道
I know.
和我们聊天的墓地管理员是个矮小老头
A little old man talked to us.He was the groundskeeper.
他解释说大部分埋在这里的人...
He explained that most of the people buried here...
...都是被多瑙河水冲上岸的
...had washed up on the bank of the Danube.
有多久的历史了?
How old are these?
大约始建于本世纪初,被称为无名公墓
Around the beginning of the century.It's called No Name Cemetery...
...因为他们大都不知道姓甚名谁
...because they often didn't know who those people were.
要不就是有名无姓
Maybe a first name, that's all.
为什么所有尸体都是冲上岸的?
Why were all the bodies washing up?
我猜有些是因为船只失事之类的事故
I think some were from accidents on boats and things like that.
但大部分是投河自尽的
But most of them were suicides that jumped in the river.
我喜欢这种想法--无名之人从世上消失
I always liked the idea of all those unknown people lost in the world.
我是小女孩时曾想过...
When I was a little girl,I thought...
...如果没有任何亲友知道你已经死了...
...if none of your family or friends knew you were dead...
...那就象没有真正死去
...then it's like not really being dead.
大家可以替你作最好或最坏的设想
People can invent the best and the worst for you.
我想她就在这
Here she is, I think.
没错,这个我记得最清楚
Yeah, this is the one I remember the most.
她死的时候只有13岁
She was only 13 when she died.
在我来说意味深长,我第一次来这就是13岁
That meant something to me.I was that age when I first saw this.
我现在长了10岁,可她还是13岁
Now I'm 10 years older,and she's still 13, I guess.
这很有趣
That's funny.
那边就是多瑙河
That's the Danube over there.
是条河,对吧?
That's a river, right?
是的
Yeah.
真是...
This is...
...壮观
...gorgeous.
是啊,真美
Yeah, this is beautiful.
我是指,我们赶上了...
I mean, we got....
我们赶上了日落
We got a sunset here.
-是的   -我们在摩天轮上
-Yeah.  -We got the Ferris wheel.
这就象...
It seems like...
...是个...
...this would be a....
什么?
What?
你知道的...
You know....
你的意思是不是想吻我?
Are you trying to say you want to kiss me?
你知道吗?
But you know what?
生于哪个时代并不重要
It doesn't matter what generation you're born into.
看看我的父母
Look at my parents.
68年5月事件,愤怒的年轻人反对一切
They were angry, young May ' 68 people revolting against everything.
政府,及其保守的天主教后台....
The government, their conservative Catholic backgrounds....
我出生之后,我父亲成为成功的建筑师
Then I was born, and my father became a successful architect.
他建造桥梁时我们周游世界...
We traveled around the world while he built bridges...
...当然,还有塔和别的什么
...and, you know, towers and stuff.
我是说,我真没什么可抱怨的
I mean, I really can't complain about anything.
他们爱我胜过一切...
They love me more than anything...
...我在他们努力营造的自由氛围中长大
...and I've been raised with all the freedom they fought for.
对我而言这是另一种形式的抗争
And yet, for me now,it's another type of fight.
我们总是面对相同的问题,却不知道...
We have to deal with the same shit,but we can't really know...
我讨厌这样
I hate this.
我也是,火车就要开了
Me too.The train is about to leave.
要知道那些都是废话...
You know all this bullshit we're talking about...
...不再见面?我不愿意
...not seeing each other?I don't want that.
我也不想
I don't either.
-你不想?   -我就是等这句话
-You don't? -I waited for you to say it.
你干嘛不说出来?
Why didn't you say something?
我担心你不想再见我
I was afraid you didn't wanna see me.
你想怎么做?
What do you wanna do?
也许5年后我们可以在这见面
Maybe we should meet here in five years or something.
5年?那太久了
Five years? That's a long time.
太恐怖了,象做社会学试验
It's awful. It's like a sociological experiment.
-一年行不行?   -一年,好的
-How about one year? -One year.
-6个月怎么样?  -6个月?
-How about six months? -Six months?
这里会很冷
It's gonna be freezing.
管它呢?在这见面然后去哪都行
Who cares? We come here,we go somewhere else.
从今天还是昨天算起?
Six months from now or last night?
昨天,从昨天算起6个月后,是...
Last night. Six months from last night, which was...
...6月16日
...June 16th.
9号站台,从现在起6个月后晚上6:00
So track nine, six months from now at 6:00 at night.
12月
December.
你坐火车就行,可我却得飞越重洋
It's a train ride for you,but I gotta fly all the way here.
不过我会来的
But I'm gonna be here.
-好的,我也会   -好的
-Okay, me too. -All right.
不打电话,不写信...
We won't call, write or--
不,这太难受了
No, it's depressing.
火车要开了
Your train's gonna leave.
说再见吧
Say goodbye.
再见
Bye.
Goodbye.
再见
Au revoir.
Later.
...是和谁对抗,敌人是什么
...who or, you know, what the enemy is.
我不知道是否真有这么个敌人
I don't know if there really is an enemy.
所有的父母都不会教育孩子
Everybody's parents fucked them up.
有钱人的孩子父母给予得太多,穷人的孩子则相反
Rich kids' parents gave them too much.Poor kids', not enough.
关爱太多,关爱不够
too much attention,not enough attention.
或是遗弃或是教些错误的东西
They either left or taught them the wrong things.
我父母是两个相爱并不太深的人...
My parents are just two people who didn't like each other much...
...他们结婚,生子
...who got married and had a kid.
然后尽力对我好
And they tried their best to be nice to me.
-你父母离婚了?  -是的,最终离了
-Did your parents divorce? -Yeah, finally.
他们早就该离,凑合在一起...
They should have done it sooner.They stuck together...
...是为了我和我姐姐,真是感激不尽
...for the well-being of my sister and I. Thank you very much.
我记得我母亲当着父亲的面告诉我...
I remember my mother told me right in front of my father...
...他并不是很想要我
...that he didn't really want to have me.
他发现她怀孕时很恼火
That he was pissed off when he found out she was pregnant.
生我是个大错误,这对我的思想影响很大
That I was a big mistake.That really shaped the way I think.
我习惯从一个不该存在的人的视角看世界
I always saw the world as this place where I really wasn't meant to be.
太悲哀了
That's so sad.